and welcome to Charlottesville for
another hyack
us excellent
excellent so uh my name is Charlie Hull
I am from open source connections uh we
host and run hyack and have done since
2018 um and I'm going to be giving you a
quick introduction today to how it's all
going to work Logistics things like that
and then a little introductory talk as
well and then we'll move on to our main
program so uh this is who we are open
source connections uh this isn't the
whole team some of our European
colleagues s sadly can't join us uh this
week uh we've got offices in
Charlottesville where the company was
founded Berlin Germany uh myself in
Cambridge UK and we've got clients
literally across the world and the sort
of things we're focusing on this year
are understanding and delighting your
users you know finding out what they're
doing and giving them a great experience
uh the hardcore search and AI
engineering that we all love and and
then thinking about people and process
you know the method of doing search
Improvement so yes and these lovely
people here are my colleagues they're
all here today so you've got any
questions at all please do reach out to
them um and ask anything about
Charlottesville the event uh whatever uh
they'll have a blue sticker on their
badges so you should be able to identify
them so how's it going to work this week
um to today Tuesday uh we've got two
tracks of talks this is our main theater
this is theater 5 we also have theater 7
which is halfway down the hall uh which
is where the second track will be uh the
talks go on till approximately 5:30 p.m.
and we have 15 minute breaks between the
talks give you a chance to chat grab
coffee get to know each other move
between the
rooms
[Music]
um we've got uh about 150 people signed
up online so ever make a big noise for
our online participants who are
listening
excellent um 12:30 till 2m we've got
lunch and that's uh at your own
discretion the downtown mall here at
Charlottesville is a beautiful
pedestrianized walkway we've got
restaurants cafes sandwich shops you
name it so find some friends and go and
grab some lunch you've got an hour and a
half there um I might if I get a chance
there's some recommended restaurants I
can drop into slack later but I mean to
be honest everywhere's pretty good down
here um at 4M we're going to have some
lightning talks so if you've got an idea
for a lightning talk a five minute talk
about uh something you're working on a
cool project something you want to bring
to people's
attention a crazy idea if you can please
uh direct message me in relevant slack
Charlie Hull she'll be able to find me
easily and we'll organize that during
the day and in fact the hyack conference
um Channel thank you Doug thank you Mr
Turnbull who's literally just there
messaged me with a talk thank you uh
first off the Mark um any uh it also the
channel uh the Haack conference Channel
irrelevance slack you're all in
relevance slack yeah everyone I hope so
um that's where we'll have general
information about the event any last
minute changes that kind of thing you've
got questions drop them in there we'll
do our best to answer them um and get
you need any help today or even in the
future ask an overc host uh from 5:45
we're going across the Cardinal Hall
which is about a 10-minute walk just up
the hill um and we've got a drinks
reception uh and and a buffet dinner for
everybody we're going to be outside
hopefully in there's a sort of tented
area um but there'll be always see
people wandering up that way so you
won't get
lost a few other logistic things so uh
bathrooms should be obvious that there's
some at the top here just back towards
the area there's some downstairs as well
um speakers if you before your talk if
you come to the front and make yourself
known to our av team and our hosts there
are no there's no C host in each room um
who will be also handling questions
after your talk uh we have a a
microphone we'll be running about with
but also we've got our online
participants who'll be asking questions
through Zoom chat and we'll inter leave
those questions with with questions from
the live audience so we really get the
online people involved as well I
remember last year we had Demitri Khan
asking questions from Finland which was
quite cool
um if you emailed me about an interview
after your talk this is for speakers
only please after your talk please come
to the front here there's a camera at
the other end of this stage we're just
going to do a little five minute U chat
to camera I don't know what do you
think's exciting the world of search
today that kind of thing it's a bit of
an experiment we hope it'll work but
please just come to the front even if
you're in the other room if you could
come to this room because we only have
one
camera uh
please try not to hang them out in the
doorways of the theaters because there's
only one door and it kind of blocks
people getting in and out but you can
use The Upstairs Lounge where you've
just been uh for for chat there are some
plug sockets there uh Wi-Fi you should
see the code on some Bits of Paper stuck
about um if you're on social media
please use the hastac con uh tag um and
that it's in the bottom right of the uh
the slide here we love to hear what
people are think of the event see photos
that kind of thing it's great um
speakers please send your slides to
David Fischer so we can put them on the
website and all the recordings and
slides will be available after the event
as atendees you'll get early access to
those as soon as we've edited them and
then it'll be public a little bit after
and and the last one please turn off
your flashes on your phones uh silence
them it is a movie theater after
all so that's that's the the hard stuff
out the way uh tomorrow we've got
another two tracks of talks uh first
one's really exciting one for us it's a
joint talk between open source
connections and our client Moody's on
enabling AI powered products that's
going to be fun we've got lunch again at
slightly earlier at 12:00 p.m. uh our
regular women of search slot will be at
1:30 just after lunch uh which I'm
really looking forward to and then we
have our birds of feather dinners these
have been sponsored by uh elastic pine
cone and open source connections uh
hopefully you've signed up for one if
you are around uh tomorrow evening but
if not there may be some space I think
the pine con have some space left but
hopefully we'll have a have a lovely
dinner there thank you so much to
elastic and pineco we really appreciate
it and then Thursday uh some of you will
have gone to the getting started with
the with search uh Workshop yesterday at
the OC offices we have another Workshop
that's actually really popular we've
completely sold out measuring search and
AI it's going to be led by my colleague
David fiser at the Omni Hotel that's
just this end of the downtown mall uh
it's the the big sort of orange Hotel
building just if you go out the end
there there'll be signed and for others
we're doing a search hack day at the OC
offices uh again we've got loads of
people signed up for this uh you'll be
able to sit and work with some of the
top names and search I think that's
really exciting it was great fun last
year we'll I don't know what we're going
to do or build you know we need some
ideas I have I think about that it's
about a 10-minute walk from here the
other end of the downtown
mall and this is something very
important thank you to everyone who
submitted a talk and who's speaking
today and tomorrow obviously Hast stack
wouldn't be great without talks It's
Kind this is kind of the center of all
of it we really appreciate the effort
you put into put preparing your talks
and your slides and we really couldn't
do without it and again a great shout
out to my colleague David Fischer who
handled the call for papers process we
keep this as Anonymous as possible we
really want the best talks to make it
through the process even OC people have
to go through the same process and I
don't even know who the reviewers were
this year uh so we keep it as as as uh
as open as we can so thanks
again um so that's the logistics the
introduction um but you know we're not
going to have a big flashy keynote this
year but um I thought I'd just do a
little talk today and I wanted to to
theme it around
people now over the last few years you
might working in this this field you
might have thought we're all going to be
replaced by robots by AI uh the rise of
AI has been astonishing as has the rise
in LinkedIn posts written and
Illustrated by images like
this I I mean literally my feed in
LinkedIn is just hundreds of these
things day after day
um but we have to remember software is
written by people and I'd like to talk
briefly about those people our our
search
community so we all say that we stand on
the shoulders of giants and I've been
really lucky in my career to to meet and
work with some of these these amazing
search people uh Steven Robertson uh one
of the parents of bm25
um he he was living in Cambridge I was
running a search Meetup in Cambridge and
this white-haired old chap uh on his
bicycle arrived at my Meetup and he
looked Vaguely Familiar and it's like
Stephen
Robinson um but yeah lovely chat um I
worked briefly with Martin Porter author
of the famous Porter stemma um which was
written in a language called bcpl anyone
remember
bcpl you're showing your age slightly
but uh glad to see somebody remembers it
the ancestor of languages like you know
see um anyway uh Martin white another a
great friend of mine author of many
books on Enterprise search mainly from a
a business perspective Ro police to
consider him a mentor he also started a
thing called the search Network which
some of see people are part of a
grouping of worldwide search
experts and then more recently uh Doug
and John for the relevant search book
which of course you'll be familiar with
and and there's there's other books of
course you know other books and and very
excited to hear from Tre Granger that
the AI powered search book he he is's
very nearly ready for publication it's
been a long time coming really looking
forward to that but there's other people
as well uh someone I read a lot on
LinkedIn and Twitter is Joe Christian
Bergen from the veser team um who gives
a very realistic very deeply argued very
mathematical explanation of lot of the
things we need to know in certain AI
these days um so you know huge props of
these people who get out there and
really push the knowledge
out and then we have all the devell
people
uh the devel elves I call them from
places like weier pine cone quadrant
elastic opener they are
everywhere they they pop up at
conferences you know excitedly telling
you about these you know wonderful new
developments and writing blog posts and
example code and it's great the energy
of these people is is astonishing not
sure I could do it um and we we really
appreciate them kind of showing the way
to some of the new
developments but sadly we also lose
people
Simon Hughes uh some of you will have
met and I think many of you will have
learned from Simon worked at dice.com
Home Depo and most recently
vegara uh Simon was always happy to
share his knowledge he gave multiple
presentations at Hast Stacks he was very
active on relevant slack uh and we lost
him sadly uh suddenly and unexpectedly
last year we all we do all very much
miss him I was lucky enough to have
dinner with him last year and it was a
great shock to
hear so
we thought we'd we do something to
memorialize Simon uh working with veara
his most recent employers we came up
this idea of the hug
scholarship and the idea of this it
would support people who wouldn't
otherwise be able to come to a Hast
conference um it support their you know
the ticket price some travel costs and
also give them some other things like
some free places on our OC training
courses and vecta have a a SAS platform
with credits so they have some credits
as well and it's open to those at the
beginning of their career career in
Search and Ai and we've been a bit vague
about that you know you don't have to be
a student or not a student or employed
not employed but somebody at the very
beginning who needs that kind of boost
and help this year we had 13 fantastic
applicants from across the world and we
judged them on financial need learning
need what they thought they need to
learn and and their ambition as well how
they describe themselves and what they
want to do in Search and Ai and my
fellow judges were um army Ahmad of
veara and Erica cardinus of we8 who gave
a fantastic last year in the women of
search slot um so thank you both for
helping with the judging and it was
sponsored by Vector no and so I'm very
happy to announce our winners this year
uh Maya ziv and ual marari uh who are
both here today uh say hello are you
here
excellent I'm sure you'll uh make them
both very welcome and I'm really hoping
they have a fantastic time this week um
sadly khabib shopu who was placed first
by our judges couldn't get a Visa in
time to get to the US uh so he he was
happy to pass on his uh his place but he
is joining us online from London hello
Hab hope you're you can see us um and he
also we're giving him the you know some
of the the training place in veara
credits but uh this is the first time
we've done this uh the response has been
amazing and I hope you agree it uh it it
raises you know some kind of Memorial to
to our dear old Simon um and we'll we'll
hope this carries
on so other things about people relevant
slack about six years ago we started a
small slack group to bring together
people who'd come to the first hyack I
think pretty much everyone who came to
the first hyack joined up and yeah it
was literally 50 people it's kind of
grown since then it's been an amazing
resource and I think particularly during
the pandemic years when we were all
disconnected and unable to meet in
person it was a huge help to kind of
keep connected with your you know
colleagues and search and relevance
there are channels in everything there
are channels on different engines on
vectors on Ecommerce search on jobs and
events and everything um and it's it's
really still very active um I'd like
actually to thank everyone who's you
know answered a question suggested
something useful posted a job and even
made a dad joke or you or two um I I
think that may have been you Doug
um and I do support the cause of dad
jokes so um yes my children don't like
them but never mind um and I'm very
pleased to
announce that literally in the last day
we've hit 5,000 members on relevant
slack look at that I can do animations
as well um but also the person who was
the 5000th member is here today Paul L
you were the 5000th member relevant
Slack
so long may it continue long may it grow
it's a it's a great central place for us
to hang out you know in between
conferences we'd love to go to search
conferences every week obviously but
apparently occasionally we also have to
do some work um and this is a place to
hang out in
between a subset of uh relevant slack is
the women of Search Group and this was
started back in I think 2022 by a small
group of women working in our in our
sector and thinking about addressing you
know what we what's obvious to all of us
you know the gender imbalance in in in
search in it and and to see what we what
could be done and uh particular mention
to my ex- colleague atito Aurora who's
been hugely active in this group in in
Europe in particular and to to Audrey
who you'll hear from tomorrow in the
women search slot at 1:30 p.m uh they do
things like uh training opportunities
you know Mutual support um putting you
know conference talks together helping
people give maybe give their first
conference talk um and you know Mutual
support um and it's not just women there
are there are allies in the group as
well it's very important um we have a
dinner on Wednesday night sponsored by
pine cone and the theme is celebrating
women of search U but again you don't
have to be a woman to attend but it's
it's really to to kind focus on that so
thank you pine cone we are only a small
corner of the IT industry and we know
there's historically a massive gender
imbalance um but I think this sets an
amazing example of you know what what
you can do if if you try and um remember
that we had every Hast stack there's a
photo so this year again there'll be a
photo this was hastac Europe a few years
ago um and hastac Europe again last year
and and this was last year at hastac us
so there'll be a photo I'm guessing
probably after the women and search slot
next
tomorrow and please join in as it's
great to to to um Mark the
occasion I couldn't talk about people
without talking about my OC colleagues
um
John woodell The Cider maker an alltime
musician Renee kler linguist he speaks
lots of languages incl including soili
and the best Berlin tour guide you'll
ever have the pleasure to uh be guided
around Berlin by David Fischer the
professor the educator Scott staltz The
Reluctant skier I believe and an osc
co-founder uh Raj Rajan the Natalie
dress New Yorker Jennifer who's our
financial controller who is the best at
adding up all of us luckily
um and Eric again OC co-founder and
owner and woodworker Eric makes things
out of woods and there are two
colleagues not who are not here today
sadly Daniel Wrigley who's a marksman he
competes in air pistol shooting
competition so you know don't annoy him
and uh and also Matias Kruger they're
they're not with us today but just
wanted to shout out to them I'm very
lucky to be part of this team and of
course I'm Charlie H the juggler that's
how most people know me um but what
about your search
team and really how you work together as
search team is is vital so I I think
there's various people in a search team
I mean firstly we have the relevance
Engineers you know the people really
with their fingers in the search engine
but it's not just you just just because
you know your way around a solar config
file or elastic DSL doesn't mean you're
the only person that's important on the
search team um we've got the search
product owners people who kind of own
search people who drive the change
really
important um people who don't know
they're in the search
team so you know content authors
managers ux designers they all
contribute to search but they probably
don't necessarily consider them part of
the you know the search team they just
know dip in occasionally but they are
important we always say you know content
is terrible you're still not going to be
able to fix it with search so that's a
really important part um the people new
to search the last few years we've had
this whole sthe of people turning up who
have come to search maybe from ml or the
you know the AI side of thing data
science and they're suddenly coming into
our community and discovering you know
what matters in Search and and sometimes
some of the problems you know we we have
actually already solved um and there's
you know it's a great coming together of
Two Worlds I
think the biggest search teams and two
examples here um our clients um Otto uh
in Germany when Europe's biggest
e-commerce science sites I think they've
got well over a hundred people in their
search team in fact they've got multiple
teams um and Home Depot legendarily has
one of the biggest search teams you can
possibly imagine but this brings its own
challenges if you've got multiple teams
all working on search how do they
communicate how do they collaborate what
are the
dependencies so you know having a
massive search team is you know not
doesn't always make things simpler
sometimes it makes things more
complicated it's one of the things we do
at OC is help work with you know search
teams help people people make their
search teams efficient and
effective um the smallest search
teams um you know sometimes it's a
handful of people sometimes isn't
considered very important by the
organization and therefore you know
you're expected to do a lot with you
know very few people in fact sometimes
it's just
you um on your own running search for a
massive organization or a small
organization but um I will say you know
a message from the rest of us here we've
got you back you with you know with
friends today you'll be able to
hopefully take a lot away from this
event and um maybe not you know feel
quite so lonely when you go back to your
business and you're the only C
person and
lastly the people of hyack everyone
who's come this
week by coming together to share
knowledge and Hast Stack's always been
about this Spirit of sharing knowledge
again we don't take sponsorship for the
event we have a neutral um Anonymous cfp
process we want the very best talks we
want people to learn from each other we
want you to tell you the stuff that
works but also importantly the stuff
that doesn't
work um and by coming together to share
knowledge you're actively pushing the
state-of-the-art forward that's
important by coming here you've made a
choice to try and make search and AI
better and I think you know well done
all of you for making that
choice and I think you know my last
message here is really you know take
care of your people and they'll take
care of
search thank you very
much so that's my little mini not really
a keynote keynote to kick us off we're
going to have a short break now and our
first set of scheduled talks will start
start at quarter 2 the hour uh in here
we have one talk and then we have
another talk in the other theater so
please check your schedules they're also
posted on the doors um and I hope you
have a wonderful Hast stack I look
forward to meeting as many of you as I
possibly can and do please forgive me
I'll be buzzing about all over the place
doing I may not have 30 seconds with
everyone but welcome to hyack and I hope
you have a fantastic week